Spire American Revolutionary War Collection
Spire American Revolutionary War Collection
1667-1878
1748-1799
Spire, Nancy Woodson.
1 linear ft.
Collection of letters, journals, account books and other documents dating from or relating to the American Revolution. Also includes material relating to the Fisher, Rapalje and Wilkins families in New York State.
4041768
Biographical History
The Spire collection contains material relating to William Duer, William Alexander Lord Stirling, and to the Fisher, Rapalje and Wilkins families, among others. The material was collected by Nancy Woodson Spire (Mrs. Lyman J. Spire) as one of her research interests.
William Alexander, Lord Stirling (1726-1783) was an American major-general during the American Revolutionary War. Serving first as a Colonel in the New Jersey militia, he eventually rose to the rank of brigadier general for the entire Continental Army. A respected tactician, he commanded forces at the battles of Long Island, Short Hills, Brandywine, Germantown and Monmouth.
William Duer (1743-1799) was a British-born American lawyer, developer, and speculator from New York City. He served in the Continental Congress, participated in the convention that framed the New York Constitution, and was a signer of the United States Articles of Confederation. He married Catherine Alexander, daughter of William Alexander, Lord Stirling, and at least one document in the collection suggests he was also acquainted with the Wilkins family (Conveyance, William Dewer [Duer?] to States [Staats] Wilkins and Ann Smythe 1830).
John Fisher (dates unknown) was a lawyer and served as a Justice of the Peace for Kings County, New York; he was also involved in land speculation in central New York State.
Garret Rapalje (b. 1730), also spelled Gerrit or Garrit, was descended from Joris Jansen Rapalje, one of the earliest settlers of New Amsterdam. Garret's parents were George Janse Rapalje and Diana (Middagh) Rapalje. He married Helena de Nyse (b. 1732), and made his living as an importer in New York City. During the 1760s he was an assistant alderman of the City. During the Revolutionary War, Rapalje was a Loyalist, and later left New York City for New Orleans. He and his wife had four children: Garret II, George, Anne (b. 1762; married Jacob Wilkins, below), and Jacques. [Information taken from the New-York Historical Society http://www.nyhistory.org/exhibit/garret-rapalje-b-1730]
John Wilkins Sr. (1733-1809) was born in Pennsylvania. According to a manuscript in the collection, his paternal grandfather emigrated to Pennsylvania from Wales and his maternal grandfather came from Ireland. He served as Captain in Spencer's Regiment during the American Revolution; his oldest son, John Jr. (1761-1816), enlisted at sixteen as a surgeon's mate and eventually (1796) rose to the rank of Quartermaster General. After the way, Wilkins undertook several business ventures and served as a Justice of the Peace in Pennsylvania. He was married twice and (again according to his memoir in the collection) had eleven children with each of them, including two "lunatick" children.
Jacob Wilkins (born circa 1735) was a brass founder, grocer, and merchant of old New York. It is likely that he was related to John Wilkins but this cannot be established. Jacob Wilkins married Hannah Betts in 1762, and they had six children: John, Jacob, William, Ann, Hannah (b. 1779), and Augustus (later a physician in Louisiana). He was married again in 1793, to Ann Rapalje, and they had two children, Helen D. and States (or Staats) Wilkins. Ann Rapalje Wilkins later married a Charles Smith or Smyth.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Spire American Revolutionary War Collection consists of letters, journals, account books and other documents, the bulk of which date from or relate to the American Revolution (1775-1783). The material is divided into series based on the person to whom it primarily relates, though the observant researcher will note that there is considerable overlap. An alphabetical index of correspondents is provided at the end of this finding aid.
The American Revolutionary War papers (1765-1785) includes correspondence, a few fragments and envelopes; an autobiographical manuscript of and by John Wilkins, Sr.; and a group of military records. The papers represent individuals from both patriot and loyalist groups. Correspondence includes letters to Sir John Johnson and Governor George Clinton. The military records include an account book of the New York Department of the British Forces, oaths of allegiance to King George and to the new republic, a muster roll of Wentworth's Volunteers, and other items.
The William Alexander, Lord Stirling papers (1775-1783) includes five letters from Alexander to others (two to John Hancock, one to Governor George Clinton of New York, one to the "President of Congress," and one to a Captain FitzRandolph).
The William Duer papers (1784-1792) consists of a small amount of correspondence and a few legal and financial documents. One relates to the Scioto Land Company.
The John Fisher papers (1768-1826) primarily relate to Fisher's responsibilities as Justice of the Peace of Kings County. The correspondence, approximately 100 items, is with business associates, family, and public officials (including one dated 1798 to Timothy Pickering, third U.S. Secretary of State). Legal and financial records include accounts, agreements, indentures, memoranda, petitions, receipts, summonses, warrants and others. Interesting items include an "order of bastardy" filed against Samuel Mitchell and Nelly Lewis (1795-1796) for the birth of a child out of wedlock, a warrant for the arrest of Nathaniel Price for the rape of Unis Williamson (1797), and a resolution for the formation of a New York morality society "to aid magistrates in suppressing vice and immorality on the Lord's Day" (1790).
The Garret Rapalje papers (1667-1830) contains correspondence and legal documents, including a genealogy of the Rapalje family. One item (Conveyance, William Dewer [Duer?] to States [Staats] Wilkins and Ann Smythe 1830) suggests a connection with William Duer.
Miscellaneous material (1752-1878) at the end of the collection comprises correspondence and legal and financial documents. The correspondence includes a latter from Rufus King, Massachusetts lawyer, politician and diplomat. Legal and financial documents include accounts, agreements, bills of exchange, indentures, summonses, warrants and wills. A few of the documents relate to Garret Rapalje or John Fisher. Of particular interest is a Prussian passport or travel authorization from 1836, indicating that the bearer, one Caspar Beckschaefer, sailed from Bremen to New Orleans.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence in each section is arranged chronologically. An alphabetical index of correspondents is provided at the end of this finding aid. Other material is arranged alphabetically by type or title.
Related Material
SCRC has considerable material relating to the early days of New York State; please see our New York State History and Ephemera subject page for more information.
Separated Material
The original donation also included several hundred printed works which have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to and search on "Nancy Woodson Spire" to locate these items.
Two items that were at one time part of this collection -- "Journal of Voyage, Plymouth to New York" by Edward Gould and "New Jersey Boundary Dispute" -- have been removed and made into their own collections (SC 124,
Iris Ship's log
and SC 125,
New Jersey Boundary Document
).
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; Alexander, William, 1726-1783.; Duer, William, 1747-1799.; Fisher, John, fl. 1768-1828.; Johnson, John, Sir, 1742-1830.; King, Rufus, 1755-1827.; Rapalje, Garret.; Wilkins, John, 1733-1810.; Wilkins, Jacob, b. 1735?; Rapalje family.; Wilkins family.; Great Britain. -- Army -- Colonial forces -- New York (State); Scioto Land Company.; Brooklyn (New York, NY) -- History.; Cayuga County (NY) -- History.; New York (NY) -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; New York (NY) -- History -- 1775-1865.; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783.; Account books.; Affidavits.; Agreements.; Correspondence.; Indentures.; Loyalty oaths.; Memoirs.; Petitions.; Summonses.; Warrants.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Nancy Woodson Spire, 1963-1968.
Gift of Lyman Spire, 1968-1971.
Inventory
- American Revolution material
  - Correspondence
    - Letters, 1765-1785 (Box 1)
    - Fragments and envelopes, 1775-1777 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts
    - Autobiographical manuscript, John Wilkins Sr., 1807; Revolutionary War general, born 1733; handwritten copy; title page reads "Copy of a Manuscript Autobiography of John Wilkins, Sr."; includes sketches of some genealogical trees with surnames Wilkins, Parker, Denny,
  - Military records
    - Account book, New York Department of British Forces, 1777-1782; account book of Col. Innes, Inspector General of Provincial Forces, and of Capt. Rooke at Philadelphia (Box 1)
    - Affidavit, Theophilus Antony, 12 Jun 1781; oath of allegiance to King George III (Box 1)
    - Affidavit, George Freeland, 27 Dec 1776; oath of allegiance to King George III (Box 1)
    - Affidavit, John W. Vredenbergh, 8 Jun 1781; oath of allegiance to King George III (Box 1)
    - Affidavit, Israel Williams, 3 Feb 1775; declaration of loyalty to American colonial independence (Box 1)
    - Assignment on soldiers discharges, Peter Buchez, 1 May 1795 (Box 1)
    - Assignment on soldiers discharges, Joseph Carly, 7 Jul 1790 (Box 1)
    - Assignment on soldiers discharges, blank form (Box 1)
    - Certificate for sale of saltpeter, East Haddam, Connecticut, 11 Jun 1776 (Box 1)
    - Checks issued by M. Weare, Nov 1782; to Daniel Carpenter and Capt. Othniel Thomas (Box 1)
    - Confiscation order for property of Benjamin Mulberry Holmes of Massachusetts Bay, 1780; for giving "Aid and Comfort" to "the King of Great-Britain, his Fleets and Armies, Enemies of the said Province"; includes typed transcript (Box 1)
    - Examination of Colonel Beverley Robinson, 1789; regarding the army's cost for hire of a waggon and driver (Box 1)
    - Muster roll for Wentworth's Volunteers, New York District, Dec 1780; no names are given, just numbers of people at each rank (Box 1)
    - Requisition and report, South Carolina Royalist First Battalion, 1779; "report on forage, baggage, and battalion money" (Box 1)
    - Residence permit for David Kennedy of New York City, 5 May 1781 (Box 1)
- William Alexander, Lord Stirling papers
  - Correspondence
    - Letters, 1775-1783; includes typed transcriptions for some of the letters (Box 1)
- William Duer papers
  - Correspondence
    - Letters, 1784-1792; many in French; includes two undated items in French relating to the Scioto Land Company (Box 1)
  - Legal and financial papers
    - Accounts payable, William Duer / Davis Strachan, 1774-1784 (Box 1)
    - Articles of agreement, William Playfair and Claude Naudet, 17 Mar 1790; in French (Box 1)
    - Letter of credit, Jean J. DeBarth to William Duer, 30 Jun 1786 (Box 1)
- John Fisher papers
  - Correspondence
    - Letters, 1768; 1791-1797,; 1800-1814; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Letters, 1816-1820; 1826 (Box 2)
    - Letters, undated (Box 2)
  - Legal and financial papers
    - Accounts payable, 1818-1819 (Box 2)
    - Accounts receivable, 1815-1817 (Box 2)
    - Articles of agreement, Powel I. Amerman and John Fisher, 1812 (Box 2)
    - Articles of agreement, Elijah Hill and John Fisher and James Clarke, 1805 (Box 2)
    - Articles of agreement, Benjamin Hough and John Fisher and James Clarke, 1811 (Box 2)
    - Articles of agreement, Nathan Leonard and John Fisher, 1802 (Box 2)
    - Bills of exchange, John Fisher to Charles McMullen [McMullins?], 1796 (Box 2)
    - Conveyance, John Fisher to Abner Brown, 1818; for sale of land (Box 2)
    - Indenture, John Fisher to John McKesson, 1790; appears to relate to sale of land (Box 2)
    - Memorandum on disbursements for the poor of Brooklyn, 1796 (Box 2)
    - Memoranda on the mortgage of Barzilla Clarke, 1807 (Box 2)
    - Order of bastardy, Samuel Mitchell and Nelly Lewis, 1795-1796 (Box 2)
    - Petition against storing gunpowder in Village of Brooklyn, 1803 (Box 2)
    - Petition regarding increase of ferryage rates from New York City to Nassau, 1801 (Box 2)
    - Petitions from ferry masters, New York City to Nassau, 1801 (Box 2)
    - Petition for removal of King's County Clerk, undated (Box 2)
    - Receipts, Manhattan Company Stock Purchase, 1800 (Box 2)
    - Recognizances for license to operation of inn or tavern, May 1796; three separate licenses, to William Duryea, Peter Prerine[?], and John Smith (Box 2)
    - Registration of invention, Johannes Lott, 1801; for a "swedging machine" having to do with the smithying of spikes, nails, brads and bolts; 2 copies (Box 2)
    - Resolution to form New York morality society, 1790; constitution of organization "to aid magistrates in suppressing vice and immorality on the Lord's Day" (Box 2)
    - Resolution to form night watch in Brooklyn, 1796; for formation of a night watch in Brooklyn, with subscribers' names (Box 2)
    - Resolution regarding transportation problems in Queen's and King's Counties, 1803 (Box 2)
    - Summons, William Baisley vs. John Van Allen, 1790; regarding debts owed to Baisley (Besley) incurred by Mrs Van Allen (Van Alan), deceased (Box 2)
    - Summons, John Corzine vs Jacob Sharpe, 1797; order to summon a jury (Box 2)
    - Summons, John Fisher vs Thomas Lawrence, 1796; regarding damages for trespass (Box 2)
    - Summons, Theodocius Hunt vs Richard Aires, 1796; regarding damages for an injury (Box 2)
    - Summons, Appolis (Appollas) Reaves[?] vs. James Roll, 1796; regarding debts owed (Box 2)
    - Summons, Isaac Sanders vs Samuel Ingles, 1797; regarding debts owed (Box 2)
    - Summons, Ezekiel Johnson Taylor vs. Appollis (Appollas) Reaves, 1790; regarding debts owed (Box 2)
    - Summons, Garret I. Vader next of kin, 1805; regarding settlement of Vader's estate with his creditors (Box 2)
    - Summons, King's County sample forms, blank forms for summons to appear and for levying judgement on a person's "Goods and Chattels" (Box 2)
    - Warrant for arrest of Richard Crosby, 1797; for debts owing (Box 2)
    - Warrant for arrest of Thomas Duncan, 1796; for stealing Nicholas Williamson's pocketbook; 2 items (Box 2)
    - Warrant for arrest of Benjamin Langton, 1796; for debts owing (Box 2)
    - Warrant for arrest of John Murray, 1796; for debts owing (Box 2)
    - Warrant for arrest of Nathaniel Price, 1797; for rape of Unis Williamson (Box 2)
    - Warrant for arrest of Peter Van Allen, 1796; for debts owing (Box 2)
    - Will of John Fisher, "a true copy", 1838; includes cover sheet stating that the validity of the will is being contested (Box 2)
- Garret Rapalje papers
  - Correspondence
    - Letters, 1754-1792; 12 folders (Box 2)
  - Legal and financial papers
    - Accounts payable, 1755-1765 (gaps) (Box 2)
    - Conveyance, William Dewer [Duer?] to States [Staats] Wilkins and Ann Smythe, 1830; for transfer of half a plantation in Baton Rouge, Louisiana; Ann is probably Ann Rapalje Wilkins Smyth, Jacob Wilkins' widow (Box 2)
    - Deposition, David Jones, 1771; regarding account books of a brewery belonging to Rapalje, Faulkner and Ten Eyck (Box 2)
    - Indenture, Brechje and Matthew Gleaves to Diana Rapalje, 1748; for sale of a house and land (Box 2)
    - Indenture, James Striker to Charles and Ann Smyth, 1823 (Box 2)
    - Land patents, extracts, John and Garret Rapalje, 1774; 1775; land in Charlotte County, on the east side of Lake Champlain; land in Tryon County, between the Cookquago branch of the Delaware and the Susquehanna (Box 2)
    - Landholding records and deeds (copies), 1667-1732; small notebook with handwritten copies of deeds, land patents, landholding records, etc.; towns mentioned include Dryden, Romulus, Lysander, Manlius, Marcellus, more (Box 2)
    - Will of Garret Rapalje, 1807; includes appointment of executors by various members of the Fisher and Rapalje families (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Genealogy of the Rapalje [Rappalje] and Remson [Remsen] families, undated (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous material
  - Correspondence
    - Letters, 1752-1878; undated (Box 2)
  - Legal and financial papers
    - Accounts payable, Michael Titus; Messrs. Watson and Murray, 1771; 1796 (Box 2)
    - Action of trespass, Margaret Van Kurean and Ephraim Brasher vs Phillip Hissick, 1783; relating to property theft and damages during the Revolutionary War (Box 2)
    - Articles of agreement, John Howe and Goldsmith Davis, 1792; for sale of household goods and furniture, includes featherbeds and "all my joyner's tools" (Box 2)
    - Assessment of damages, Captain Fordyce of the Elizabeth, 1790; amount owed to by 93 passengers picked up at sea by the Elizabeth, for "freight and salvage" (Box 2)
    - Bills of Exchange, 1764-1766; 1795 (Box 2)
      1764 - Alexander Grant to Napoleon Hart Myers, dated from Halifax
      1765 - John Munson to Joseph King; Garret Rapalje's name appears on the back
      1766 - Nicholas Bogart to Dirk Sligting Williams, in Dutch; Garret Rapalje's name appears on the back
      1795 - Johnson Butler to George Leslie, dated from Schenectady, New York
    - Bill of Health, from Port of New York, blank form to be filled out and carried by masters of vessels bound for Europe, guaranteeing that they brought no sickness with them (Box 2)
    - Broadside inviting applications for damages for "Spoilations and Ravages of the British", 1837 (Box 2)
    - Deed poll and tax statements, Indiana County, Pennsylvania, 1821-1822 (Box 2)
    - Indenture, 1791; Jacob Wilkins, Abraham Bussing, Elizabeth and Peter Mesier (Map-case 108)
    - Indentures, 1762; 1859 (Box 2)
      1762 - Henry Lane to Cornelia Norwood, for release of mortgage
      1859 - Sarah Royce to George W. McCollum, for sale of land and buildings on Sixth Avenue and 28th Street in New York City
    - Inspection certificate, Port of New York, circa 1790; blank form, in French (Box 2)
    - Inventory of the effects of John Ferrol, 1796; ferry employee, drowned December 1795 (Box 2)
    - Letter of recommendation, Henry Benfield, 1797; from the neighbors of Henry Benfield, recommending him as "a proper person to keep a tavern or publick house" (Box 2)
    - Letters testamentary, James B. Clarke for John McLane, 1791; grants Clarke power of disposition of the estate of McLane, deceased intestate (Box 2)
    - Passport, Caspar Beckschaefer [?], 1836; No. 51, issued by Prussia ("Königliche Preussische Regierung zu Arnsberg"); inside indicates he sailed from Bremen for New Orleans (Box 2)
    - Petitions, 1764; 1779,; 1785 (Box 2)
      1764 - Neate [?] & Pigou [?], requests return of duties paid on nine tons of "barr iron" shipped on the Sally John Taylor
      1779 - Ezekiel Travers to New York Legislature. for assistance after having been "Shot thru the right hand by a party of Indians, which has reduced him & his poor family Almost to the Utmost Extremity"
      1785 - petition for pardon by Capt. Stephen Chambers on behalf of Robert Moore, for counterfeiting
    - Power of attorney, James and Amasa Winchill to Joseph Chittenden, 1801; residents of Milton Township, Cayuga County; for purchase of land from John Fisher in "Brookland" (Brooklyn) (Box 2)
    - Promissory note, William Ross to Joseph Eddy, 1751; dated from Glocester (Box 2)
    - Receipts, 1782; 1796,; 1818-1819 (Box 2)
      1782 - George Taylor, for delivery of beef cattle, apparently to the military
      1796 - John Fisher, for "excise money"
      1818 - David Colon, for state and poor taxes
      1819 - David Colon, for taxes for school district #1
    - Resolution for appointment of Henry Stanton as Inspector of Wood, Brooklyn, 1799 (Box 2)
    - Summary of the School of the town of Brooklyn, 1796; trustees, masters, number of students, etc. (Box 2)
    - Summons, James Jackson vs Stephen Root, 1819; for Ralph Hodge, John Fisher, Timothy Beedle, Benjamin Dela[---], Thomas Y[---], Isaac Smith [?] and John Twopenny, to testify in a case in Onondaga County (Box 2)
    - Treasurer's account, Middlesex County, Massachusetts Colony, 1751; includes affidavit statement and signatures of auditors (Box 2)
    - Warrant, John Mitchall of Westmoreland County, 1773; for seizure of property for debts; no state or country given, possibly Pennsylvania (Box 2)
    - Will, William Spencer, 1756; mentions "my loving friends Peter Remsen and Garret Rappalje"; written on the occasion of Spencer's shipping on board the brig Johnson, commanded by John Grigg, "cruising as a Privateer against his Majestie's Enemies" (Box 2)
    - Will, Jacob Wilkins, document contesting the will of Jacob Wilkins, brought by Staats Wilkins and other heirs; mentions ownership of the Courtland (Cortlandt) Street Ferry and Steam Boat Slip in New York City (Box 2)
Index to correspondence
Letters are listed in alphabetical order by sender. The series in which each letter is filed is given in square brackets following the date, as follows: AR = American Revolution, WA = William Alexander, WD = William Duer, JF = John Fisher, GR = Garret Rapalje, and M = Miscellaneous.
Brinley, E. 1783 Mar 26 [AR], New York, to Frances Brinley
Alexander, William 1775 Dec 5 [WA], Elizabethtown, to John Hancock 1776 Mar 3 [WA], New York, to John Hancock 1776 Nov 11 [WA], Elizabethtown, to President of Congress 1779 Jan 29 [WA], Camp Middlebrook, NJ, to Capt. Fitz Randolph 1783 Jan 4 [WA], Albany, to Gov. George Clinton
Allou [?] 1790 Oct 30 [WD], New York, to William Duer
Amerman, Paul I. or Powell I. 1812 Jul 6 [JF], Auburn, NY, to John Fisher 1812 Nov 28 [JF], Aurelius, NY, to John Fisher 1813 Jul 12 [JF], Auburn, NY, to John Fisher 1814 Jan 3 [JF], Cayuga, NY, to John Fisher 1817 Apr 28 [JF], Owasco, NY, to John Fisher 1819 Apr 17 [JF], Mexico, NY, to John Fisher 1820 Mar 31 [JF], John Fisher (see also Fisher, John, 1820 Jun 14 [JF], to George B. Throupe)
Barth, Dr. 1791 Apr 15 [WD], Philadelphia, to William Duer
Beers, John 1796 Jun 3 [JF], to John Fisher
Bergen, Cornelius 1796 Mar 10 [JF], Flatbush, NY, to John Fisher
Bieveneux 1790 Oct 9 [WD], Paris, to William Duer
Birdseye, Samuel 1819 Apr 29 [JF], Pompey, NY, to James B. Clarke
Bogardus, Robert 1816 Feb 26 [JF], Newark, to John Fisher
Brinley, E. 1783 Mar 26 [AR], New York, to Francis Brinley
Buhler, John 1820 Aug 18 [JF], Baton Rouge, LA, to Diana Rapalje
Burnham, E. 1813 Jan 14 [JF], Aurora, NY, to John Fisher
Clarke, Thomas 1801 Sep 3 [JF], New York, to John Fisher
Carter, Christopher 1776 Mar 2 [AR], Philadelphia Gaol, to Committee of Safety
Chambers, Stephen 1785 Aug 2 [M], Lancaster, to unidentified
Chittenden, Joseph 1802 Mar 29 [JF], Milton [?], to John Fisher
Clark, Barnabus 1768 May 29 [JF], Boston, MA, to John Fisher
Clarke, James B. - 1795 Dec 28 [JF], to John Fisher 1813 Jun 9 [JF], Auburn, NY, to Abraham Leggett 1813 Jun 12 [JF], Montezuma, NY, to John Fisher 1814 Jul 25 [JF], Auburn, NY, to John Fisher [undated] [JF], Manlius, NY, to John Fisher